we have seen that we can if convert if
then else is a similar technique would
be very useful for a loop but can we
really if convert a loop let's go back
to our loop that loads from some memory
address
adds something to that
stores that back in memory
adds 4 to the pointer to the beginning
of the loop unless the pointer has
reached some final value
let's say that in this processor every
operation takes two cycle to do so we
will have
a stall cycle here because we need to
use r2 two cycles later
another stall cycle here because the add
needs to operate for one more cycle
before the store can see that value
there is no stow cycle here because this
ad can actually proceed immediately it
doesn't depend on the store and then the
branch gets delayed by one more cycle
because it's using the result of the add
so we have three stall cycles here and
again this is a processor where every
operation just takes two cycles we have
already seen that we can schedule this
loop differently so that we load and
then we do the add-i and then we do the
add
this way we avoid the stall cycle here
however after this ad the only things
that are left to do in this iteration of
the loop are the store and the branch we
cannot do the branch before the store so
the store has to happen here and thus we
haven't eliminated this stall cycle here
and then the branch can check r1 for
whether it reached the final value here
because
without a stall because r1 has been
manipulated here and then we have to
change this store if you remember
because the add
of a constant has moved here so that
it uses a minus four offset to
compensate for this
so we managed to eliminate two of these
store cycles but one still remains
now if you look at this branch here if
conversion would allow us to kind of do
the next iteration of the loop here
and then eliminate this branch because
it would be predicated and then we could
maybe find something here that can go
over here but the problem is that a loop
is not really suitable for if conversion
because every time we have a new
iteration we would have to introduce a
new predicate and then every new
iteration would introduce yet another
predicate and we simply cannot deal with
so many predicates and so many things
that get done only if the predicate is
true pretty much if we are executing a
million iteration loop sometimes and
sometimes only one iteration
then almost a million iterations would
have to be just predicated out which
would be very very slow so we want to do
something about loops that is like if
conversion to allow us to kind of find
things in future iterations to move here
but without really doing if conversion
so we cannot truly if convert but there
is something else we can do and that
something will be called
loop and rolling